Welcome back to
learning how to learn!
In this video, we'll explore
some exciting new research
on generative AI,
as well as how our brains form
connections when we
learn, AND how we can
use the power of
metaphors to help
us understand and
remember new information.
Remember how we've
talked about chunks,
those compact packages of
information that your
mind can easily access?
We've symbolized those
chunks as ribbons.
Let's dive a little deeper
so we can see how this
relates to what's actually
going on in our brain.
Our neurons—tiny
biological cells—
are fundamental building blocks
of learning in the brain.
We make connections between
neurons as we're learning.
The clumps of connected
neurons as we
learn something form
what we call "chunks."
The connections we make between
neurons strengthen
with practice,
forming neural
pathways that help
us recall information
more easily.
Think of it like
links in a necklace.
Each time you practice or
retrieve the information
from your own brain,
the links in the neural
necklace become stronger.
Metaphors, as it turns out,
are not just a literary device.
They play a crucial role
in how we understand and
process new information by
linking it to information
we already know.
By linking these
abstract concepts to
the more concrete, familiar
ideas already in our minds,
metaphors can help
our brains form
connections and make
sense of complex topics.
This is where generative
AI—like ChatGPT—comes in.
The flow of information
through the transformers
that are at the heart of
these AI platforms
are surprisingly like
the flow of information
through the human brain.
These powerful language models
can help us create vivid,
memorable metaphors to
explain challenging concepts.
For example, when asked to
explain the difference between
"main guard" and "scope"
in Python programming,
ChatGPT generated this metaphor:
"Think of the main guard in
a Python script as the
gatekeeper of a castle,
and scope as the various
rooms within that castle."
By relating these abstract
programming concepts
to a familiar image of a castle,
the metaphor helps us
understand and remember
the difference
between main guard
and scope more effectively.
What can be surprising is
that generative AI can
devise many different metaphors
that can be surprisingly
different from one another,
even while each metaphor
is useful in its own way.
You can almost think
of metaphors as tents,
where the tent poles pull
the tent up is
where the metaphor
is most powerfully similar
to the underlying
concept it's related to.
Different metaphors hold the
tent up at different places.
For example, if you're
trying to understand
the structure of atoms with
their nucleus and electrons,
you could use the metaphor that
atoms are similar to a school.
The nucleus is like the
principal's office,
central to the school's
functioning and decision-making.
The electrons are like
students occupying
different classrooms,
that is—energy levels—
and moving between them.
That gives two points
of commonality,
two tent poles in
our tent metaphor.
You can see, though,
that this metaphor is
also a poor fit in many places.
Or we could say that atoms
are like peaches or mangoes.
The nucleus is like a
pit at the center of
the fruit containing
most of the atom's mass.
Second, electrons
are like the pulp
of the fruit surrounding
the nucleus.
Third, the electron shells
are like the layers
of the fruit,
that is, skin, flesh,
and core, representing
different energy levels.
That's three points
of commonality
for this metaphor but obviously,
there's a lot of information
this metaphor misses.
Another metaphor for atoms
is the planetary system.
This also has three
points of commonality,
but those points are very
different from a peach or mango.
The nucleus is like
the sun at the center,
electrons orbit
around the nucleus
like planets orbiting the sun.
Different energy levels are
different orbital
distances of planets.
Those are places of good fit,
but clearly, there are
places of poor fit—
that is, the fuzzy quantum nature
of electrons and the
nucleus, for example.
We could instead replace
the solar system with
swirling clouds.
This new metaphor
captures part of
the underlying
concept of an atom in
a different way that illustrates
the fuzzy quantum
nature of the atom.
There are other metaphors
that could have
had even more points
of commonality.
For example, a city is an
interesting metaphor for atoms.
Among other things, the city has
bridges that are
like chemical bonds.
The next time you're struggling
to grasp a new concept,
try creating a metaphor
through generative AI
to help your brain form
those crucial connections.
Prompt it to give
you a metaphor for
a concept you might
be struggling to
understand. And don't hesitate
to ask for another
metaphor if you'd like.
It can be surprising
what kind of
wildly different
metaphors it can provide.
Perhaps ask it for
a metaphor that
relates to your favorite hobby.
That's all for now—
Happy learning!